[
  {
    "question": "Q. What was the purpose of the Council of Nicaea in 325?",
    "answer": "A. To resolve the issue of Arianism and the nature of Jesus, and to clarify the understanding of passages like John 14:28 and John 1:1."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What were the key statements in the Nicene Creed?",
    "answer": "A. The Son is 'of one substance with the Father' (homoousios), and 'Begotten, not made'."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What was the significance of the Edict of Thessalonica in 380?",
    "answer": "A. Christianity became the only official religion of the Roman Empire under the Theodosian emperor."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What were the key outcomes of the Council of Constantinople in 381?",
    "answer": "A. The council dealt decisively with Arianism, condemned Apollinarianism, reaffirmed Nicaea, and expanded its teaching on the Holy Spirit by affirming his Deity."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What was added to the Nicene Creed by the Council of Constantinople?",
    "answer": "A. The section on the Holy Spirit was expanded to affirm his Deity, and the Filioque clause was added by some Latin churches in the 6th century."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is the significance of the Niceno-Constantinopolitan Creed?",
    "answer": "A. It affirmed the Deity of the Holy Spirit, and stated that there is one being and three persons, with consubstantiality."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What was the outcome of the Council of Constantinople?",
    "answer": "A. Nothing was ultimately solved, and it lacked full support from East and West."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What was the purpose of the Council of Ephesus in 431?",
    "answer": "A. To affirm the title Θεοτόκος or 'Mother of God' for Mary against Nestorius, and to condemn Nestorianism and Pelagianism."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What was the significance of the title 'Mother of God'?",
    "answer": "A. It affirmed that Mary was the mother of Jesus, who was both human and divine, and therefore 'God' from the moment of his conception."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What was the outcome of the Council of Ephesus?",
    "answer": "A. The council condemned Nestorius and affirmed the title 'Mother of God' for Mary, but cautioned against using the term to exalt Mary."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What was the purpose of the Council of Chalcedon in 451?",
    "answer": "A. To condemn Eutychianism and establish the hypostatic union as orthodox doctrine."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What did the Chalcedonian Creed affirm?",
    "answer": "A. Christ in one person, two natures, without mixture or division, with a'reasonable soul'."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is the hypostatic union?",
    "answer": "A. The union of Christ's divine and human natures, existing 'without confusion, without change, without division, without separation'."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is Adoptionism?",
    "answer": "A. Christ was not divine, but a man adopted by God and imparted with the Spirit."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is Antinomianism?",
    "answer": "A. Denies the need to obey the OT law. Was a popular component of Gnosticism and has persisted in various forms down through the centuries."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is Arianism?",
    "answer": "A. Jesus is less than God, but more than a man (a lesser god). Denies fullness and uniqueness of Christ’s deity. “There was when He was not.” Arius believed Jesus was an intermediary between God and man, yet still a creature. He refused the divinity of Christ because he felt this would challenge his monotheistic belief. Condemned at Nicaea 325AD. Mormons and J.W.’s would have similar views. John 1 and Col. 1 would speak against this view."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is Apollinarianism?",
    "answer": "A. Denied that Christ possessed a human soul and the full humanity of Christ to protect the doctrine that Jesus was without sin. The Divine nature occupies the place of the soul in the person of Christ, only partially human. Condemned by the Council of Constantinople."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is Docetism?",
    "answer": "A. Jesus is wholly divine and only seemed to be a man but was truly a pure spirit-being uncontaminated by the material world. Thus, Jesus did not truly 'die' on the cross. Docetism was present as early as the 1st century, was combated by the apostle John in 1 John 4:2 and became an important aspect of Gnosticism."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is Donatism?",
    "answer": "A. Fourth century North Africans who started a separate church, and highly emphasized holiness and the purity of the visible church. Primary opponent was Augustine. Donatism started after the persecutions of Diocletian, when the Donatists refused to accept back into the church those who had poured a libation to the emperor or had forfeited Bibles to be burned."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is Ebionism?",
    "answer": "A. Denied incarnation and virgin birth. Believed Jesus was a prophet but not savior. Used Hebrews exclusively."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is Eutychianism?",
    "answer": "A. Denied the human nature of Christ (similar to Apollinarianism). Claims that Christ had two natures before the incarnation and the human nature was absorbed into the divine nature at the incarnation."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is Gnosticism?",
    "answer": "A. A group of heresies, primarily in the 2nd century, that taught a radical dualism between the physical and the spiritual, proclaimed salvation through knowledge, and had a docetic view of Christ.\nViews:\n- Matter is false and evil, and it must be rejected in favor of spirit.\n- Jesus was a teacher who revealed the secret knowledge necessary for salvation.\n- Most famous form is represented by Valentinus.\n- Works include Gospel of Thomas, Gospel of Philip, and Gospel of Truth.\n- Major opponents included Irenaeus, Tertullian, and Epiphanius."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is Kenoticism?",
    "answer": "A. Taught a reduction of God's deity in Christ at the incarnation; a misunderstanding of Phil. 2 with the idea Christ fully emptied himself of his deity."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is Manicheism?",
    "answer": "A. Third century form of Gnosticism founded by Mani, which continued for several centuries. Augustine was an adherent for a time, and then became a vigorous opponent. Addressed problem of evil by separating God from evil."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is Marcionism?",
    "answer": "A. 2nd century heresy that taught a strong distinction between the vengeful God of the OT and the God of the NT, and only accepted a reduced NT canon. Marcion formed a separate church that became a rival to orthodox churches. Some aspects of Marcionism were similar to Gnosticism, in that it taught Jesus was not born into the material world, but merely appeared at age 29. His sufferings were only apparent, not real."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is Monarchianism?",
    "answer": "A. Third century heresy that stresses the oneness of God to such an extent that it denies the personal distinctiveness of the Son and Holy Spirit.\nTwo Forms:\n- Dynamic (Adoptionism): The Father alone is God, and the Son was merely a man who was specially endowed with the Holy Spirit. Denied the logos teaching of John.\n- Modalism/Sabellianism: God is one person who appears in three different modes: the Father, Son and Holy Spirit."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is Monophysitism?",
    "answer": "A. Jesus is divine but has human attributes. The incarnate Christ had only a single, divine nature, clad in human flesh – also called Eutychianism after Eutyches, a leading defender of this doctrine."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is Montanism?",
    "answer": "A. Stressed Spirit and miracles. Believed dispensation of the Son had ended and church was dispensation of the Spirit."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is Monothelitism?",
    "answer": "A. Jesus is God – a man without a human will."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is Nestorianism?",
    "answer": "A. Believed that the divine and human nature of Christ were two separate persons. Condemned at the Council of Ephesus."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is Pelagianism?",
    "answer": "A. Emphasized human free will and moral responsibility, denied original sin, and taught salvation through meritorious obedience."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is Sabellianism?",
    "answer": "A. Known as Modalism; teaches that the unipersonal God reveals himself in three ‘modes’ which means there are not permanent distinctions in the Godhead."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is Socinianism?",
    "answer": "A. The Son of God did not exist until he was born a man, denying the eternal Trinity."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What is Subordinationism?",
    "answer": "A. The Son and Holy Spirit are subordinate to God the Father and are not completely equal in power and glory."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What was the First Ecumenical Council and when was it held?",
    "answer": "A. The Council of Nicaea, held in 325 AD."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What was the controversy that the Council of Nicaea was convened to resolve?",
    "answer": "A. Arianism, which denied the divinity of Jesus Christ."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What did the Council of Nicaea affirm?",
    "answer": "A. The divinity of Jesus, declaring him to be 'of one substance' (homoousios) with God the Father."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What was established by the Council of Nicaea?",
    "answer": "A. The Nicene Creed, which remains a fundamental statement of Christian orthodoxy to this day."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What was the Second Ecumenical Council and when was it held?",
    "answer": "A. The Council of Constantinople, held in 381 AD."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What was the controversy that the Council of Constantinople was convened to resolve?",
    "answer": "A. The controversy over the divinity of the Holy Spirit."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What did the Council of Constantinople affirm?",
    "answer": "A. The divinity of the Holy Spirit, declaring him to be 'of one substance' with God the Father and Jesus Christ."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What was established by the Council of Constantinople?",
    "answer": "A. The reaffirmation and addition to the Nicene Creed, and the condemnation of Apollinarism."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What was the Third Ecumenical Council and when was it held?",
    "answer": "A. The Council of Ephesus, held in 431 AD."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What was the controversy that the Council of Ephesus was convened to resolve?",
    "answer": "A. Nestorianism, which denied the unity of Jesus' human and divine natures."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What did the Council of Ephesus affirm?",
    "answer": "A. The unity of Jesus' natures, declaring him to be both fully human and fully divine."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What was established by the Council of Ephesus?",
    "answer": "A. The Virgin Mary as 'Theotokos' (Mother of God)."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What was the Fourth Ecumenical Council and when was it held?",
    "answer": "A. The Council of Chalcedon, held in 451 AD."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What was the controversy that the Council of Chalcedon was convened to resolve?",
    "answer": "A. Monophysitism, which denied Jesus as having two distinct, inseparable natures."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What did the Council of Chalcedon affirm?",
    "answer": "A. The two natures (hypostatic union) of Jesus, declaring him to be both fully human and fully divine."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What was established by the Council of Chalcedon?",
    "answer": "A. The Chalcedonian Definition, which remains a fundamental statement of Christian orthodoxy to this day."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What was the Fifth Ecumenical Council and when was it held?",
    "answer": "A. The Council of Constantinople II, held in 553 AD."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What was the controversy that the Council of Constantinople II was convened to resolve?",
    "answer": "A. The Three Chapters, which were writings that seemed to support Nestorianism."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What did the Council of Constantinople II affirm?",
    "answer": "A. The condemnation of the Three Chapters and the reaffirmation of the Chalcedonian Definition."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What was the Sixth Ecumenical Council and when was it held?",
    "answer": "A. The Council of Constantinople III, held in 680-681 AD."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What was the controversy that the Council of Constantinople III was convened to resolve?",
    "answer": "A. Monothelitism, which denied the human will of Jesus."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What did the Council of Constantinople III affirm?",
    "answer": "A. The two wills of Jesus, declaring him to have both a human will and a divine will."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What was established by the Council of Constantinople III?",
    "answer": "A. The Orthodox doctrine of the two wills of Jesus."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What was the Seventh Ecumenical Council and when was it held?",
    "answer": "A. The Council of Nicaea II, held in 787 AD."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What was the controversy that the Council of Nicaea II was convened to resolve?",
    "answer": "A. Iconoclasm, which prohibited the use of icons in worship."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What did the Council of Nicaea II affirm?",
    "answer": "A. The use of icons in worship, declaring them to be a legitimate way of expressing devotion to God."
  },
  {
    "question": "Q. What was established by the Council of Nicaea II?",
    "answer": "A. The Orthodox doctrine of the veneration of icons."
  }
]
